{
  "reference_number": "9529",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Somebody has to pay for whatever efforts the Government does to reduce carbon emissions. Ultimately that cost will fall on the\n\n citizens of New Zealand. Zero carbon emissions would put a huge burden on to New Zealand citizens that is senseless and\n unjustified."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Emissions Trading Scheme is a swindle that has created a large consulting industry for no worthwhile purpose other than to\n\n advise enterprises how to manipulate the scheme to their advantage and a bureaucracy to manage a very complex scheme.\n Government should abandon the Emissions Trading Scheme and replace it with a direct and transparent tax on the carbon content of\n fossil fuels as they are extracted or at port of entry into New Zealand. The tax would raise the price of fuel to New Zealand consumers\n\n but market forces would determine what citizens are prepared to pay to support Government carbon limiting policies."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Major carbon emitting countries do little to curb their carbon emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "We are not the 5 year planned Soviet Union. We are a liberal market economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "We are a democracy not a communist state. The current government cannot fix what future governments can do or not do."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We are a democracy not a communist state. The current government cannot fix what future governments can do or not do."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Government action should be influenced by events and information available at the time of decision making and not bound by past\n\nviews."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "All plans are obsolete from the time they are published."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It would be great to get some feedback as to what the Emissions Trading Scheme has or has not achieved."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Advise Government to abandon it."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Provided the Commision takes note from experts whose views have a sound and measured basis and not all on airy fairy models.\n\nFour variables in a model is sufficient to draw whatever you want."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Realistic projections should be used to frame Government policies to safeguard the interests of New Zealand citizens."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Insurance industry."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Any Government scheme should not include agriculture. The question is what damage are humans doing to the environment by\nburning fossil fuels that have have been in the ground for eons. It has nothing to do with agriculture that humans have practiced for\nthe 10,000 years."
    }
  ]
}
